So, what I want to do today is um
continue our discussion on AI project
strategy. So, if you're building a deep
learning system
for some task, and today um for the
first part of today I'm going to use the
speech recognition uh
voice-activated device example, and then
for the second half I'm going to use the
kind of AI deep researcher example. But,
what I want to do is um walk you through
a couple concrete examples of, you know,
projects you might work on. Um um
And let you understand what it feels
like to be in the thick of building AI
system, making day-to-day decisions on
what to do next. Uh
I find that I I think it's important Let
me say before, understanding the
algorithms is important. So, in this
class you learn a lot here from the
online videos about the uh deep learning
algorithms, how to build pipelines. But,
even beyond understanding how the
algorithms work,
what really drives performance is a
team's ability to have an efficient
development process. How do you tune
hyperparameters? How do you collect
data? When you try something and it
doesn't work the first time, which it
often doesn't, what do you do next? This
skill in making those decisions is what
often makes a massive, literally 10x
difference in productivity.
And as I was reflecting as preparing
for, you know, what to say to you today,
I was reflecting on quite a few projects
where um
that 10x difference in productivity is
is is is really not an exaggeration,
right? Maybe more than 10x, but I've
literally seen many teams in many, you
know, well-known companies with good
brands um
spend a year work on a project that I
will see a more skilled team execute in
like a month, right? So, these
differences in skill are real.
And one of the challenges um for many
people learning this is
if you work for some company, maybe you
work on a different project every year
or two, right? But, so it takes you like
you know, 2 years of every 2 years or a
year of your life to gain experience on
one more project. And then after, I
don't know, 10 years you finally seen 10
projects and pretty experienced. Uh
but, what I want to do is in today's
class walk you through a few concrete
examples of projects that similar to the
ones kind of simplified versions of
stuff that I've seen myself to try to
accelerate your hands-on experience
looking at these projects and thinking
through if you are the one in the hot
seat building a system and it works or
it doesn't work or there's a problem or
whatever, making those decisions for
what you would do. So, try to get you
through that um today with a couple
examples rather than you having to spend
years and years of your life to finally
see a small number of examples of how
these projects can be driven.
Okay.
So, the first mo- the first of the two
motivating examples I'm going to use
today is um
building a voice-activated
device. Uh
and in my house I have, you know, like a
Amazon Echo, right? I have a lot of them
actually. And I think it's a delightful
experience. But, those devices like that
uh Amazon Echo or Google Home or the um
Apple Siri HomePod, uh they require
quite a bit of setup, right? They
require some setup. You got to connect
to the Wi-Fi, figure out a way to
connect to your phone, blah on. So, you
know, actually for a long time, even
though I I built smart speakers, um for
a long time in my house I had one light
bulb connected to my home Wi-Fi
internet, you know, because it's just so
much of a hassle to set things up. I I
think now I have two light bulbs
connected in my house. I guess I should
actually connect more stuff. Um
But, so for this motivating example, I
want to talk about if you are uh part of
a startup building a new product that um
makes it much easier to get these
voice-controlled devices without the
user needing to do this home Wi-Fi setup
process, right? So, um
you know,
not like very good at drawing.
But, if you could go to some store and
buy a desk lamp,
and the desk lamp already has a name, um
let's call this lamp Robert. And you
could just take it, plug it into the
electricity, plug it on your desk, and
say, "Robert, turn on." And then it
turns on. Say, "Robert, turn off." It
turns off without needing to be
connected to the internet, using cloud
access, and all that. Then that would
give users a easier setup experience. Um
there's a project that my friends and I
actually discussed a few years ago that
we thought would actually be a decent
startup idea. We decided not to do it
because we had two other ideas that we
even more excited about. But, we thought
that actually, you know, like a
reasonable reasonable startup idea to
build a little IC circuit, little
integrated circuit, to sell to say lamp
manufacturers and other device
manufacturers to make it really easy if
if say some company sells lamps to build
little things so they can very quickly
make their devices voice-enabled. And if
you have a few pre-built names, maybe
give the users a choice. You can call
your lamp Robert or Lena, you know, or
or or
I don't know, or Johnny or I don't know,
Alice or whatever. Um um have a little
switch, then users could um
just buy a lamp, put it down, and then
immediately have it be voice-controlled
without needing to worry about how do I
get this onto my Wi-Fi network? And if
my internet is down, then my whole house
stays dark as well. There's all things
like that. Right? Um
And and I actually did once have an I
was building a lot of voice assistants.
I actually set up my office to have a
lot of voice-controlled devices. So, had
different names for different lamps.
Standing desk has name as well. So, I'd
say, I forget what my desk name was, you
know, like you know, "Jonathan, go
higher." or whatever. And then and then
my standing desk would go up and down.
So, it's actually pretty cool.
Um
So, what I want you So,
uh just for today's illustration,
probably we should give the different uh
devices different names because you
can't have every device in your house
called Robert. Otherwise, you say,
"Robert, turn on." The whole house
illuminates. Then "Robert, turn off."
Whole house is plunged into darkness.
So, we found out you do need different
devices to have different names. Uh but,
just for today, I'm going to use um as
illustration the task of training uh
neural network, of building a system
that detects when someone says, "Robert,
turn on." And you need kind of Robert,
turn on, Robert, turn off. If you have a
choice of names, it would be Lena, turn
on, Lena, turn off, a variety of handful
of options of names. But, just for
simplicity, I'm going to worry only
about detecting the phrase um
Robert, turn on.
Right? And what do we do for this? You
can rinse and repeat to get the turn off
command and a handful of other names to
make it user-selectable. What you know,
what name do you want to give this
thing? Okay?
So, um
this is something that I'll need to run
on device, uh small IC circuits. And my
And And I'm going to ask you a question,
right?
Um
>> [snorts]
>> when you've graduated from CS230 or
maybe when you graduate from Stanford,
if you are the CTO of a startup
responsible for building this, um
what would you do, right? So, call it
out. So, imagine you just graduated from
CS230 or just graduated from Stanford,
and you're the CTO of a startup,
and you want to build this lamp that can
turn on when anyone says, "Robert, turn
on."
How would you approach this problem? And
I know this is an incredibly open-ended
question, and it turns out life is
incredibly open-ended, right? You
graduate from CS230, you have to decide
what to do. So, if this is what you're
doing, uh if you feel like raising your
hand, uh call it out. If you want to
build this product,
what's the first thing you do? How would
you think about it?
Go for it.
Yeah, cool. Yeah, right. So, get some
like a open-source speech-to-text model
or something, and then see if you can
run it. Yeah, that'd be a good start.
Anything else?
Go ahead.
All right, so three models, one to
detect Robert, and then one that
I see.
I see. Cool. Right. Okay, right. So, so
uh
a few models to detect Robert,
understand rest of the sentence, or
detect the sound.
Cool. Go for it.
Oh, sorry. Say again?
So,
Okay. Oh, I see. Oh, like a It's like a
Siamese network. We actually teach a
Siamese network later in this class
where something that inputs two audio
files and decides they're saying the
same words. So, you can more easily
generalize to new words than the Robert.
Cool. No, that's actually really
interesting. Yeah, go go for it.
Oh, sorry. You would just
connect up your device to Siri?
I see. Okay, cool. Yeah. Right, yeah.
That sounds It sounds like a different
product than this if if we need to
connect it to your cell phone and all
that, though. Yeah, cool. All right.
So, let let me just lots of interesting
ideas. Let me just make some
observations. Um
So, I find that when building software
products, um
uh there's actually lots of good ideas
or lots of visual things you could try,
but you know, as as you heard me mention
a few weeks ago, I think one of the
strongest predictors for the odds of you
building something compelling is speed.
So, I find that
of all of these ideas, I think some are
better than others, but it doesn't but
but whether the the ideas, you know, a
bit better a little bit worse, it is
important, but it's actually secondary
to how quickly you can just get
something built. So, if you're actually
the CTO of a startup like this, I'd
encourage you to look and say, "All
right, what can we build you know,
today? Or what can we build maybe in a
week?" And um try any of these
architecture choices and build it and
see what happens. Because even if what
you build is a little bit less, you
know, good, um you can find out all in 2
days, you know, and you can course
correct very quickly.
Uh I've actually worked I've actually
built a lot of smart speakers. Um so, I
have maybe first hand experience of this
and I'll just share some things that I
happen to know that there's no reason
you would know, but it it turns out that
um
let's see. At least today, general
purpose um
speech recognition is still a little bit
heavy weight. Uh it takes quite a lot
of, you know, processing power or is a
bit expensive to run on an edge device
if you want to make this like a just a
few dollars. Um
but it turns out that if you look at the
um smart speakers,
uh there's usually um
uh
uh if you want to train a neural network
just to detect one phrase, uh
be it a phrase like, you know, "Okay,
Google" or "Hey, Siri" or "Alexa" or
whatever, any of the smart speaker
trigger words,
that can be done with a fairly small
neural network. Although, to your point,
if you want to do different neural
networks, different words, you'll need
to swap out different neural networks. I
won't even try to repeat that. That's a
So, but if you have only a small handful
of names, phrases one to take, I think I
think that'll be okay.
And then,
one other piece of advice I would give
um if you're embarking on this is the
first thing I would do actually if I was
working on this for the first time is is
actually a literature search.
Um and it turns out that uh you know,
what I think we're fortunate that the AI
world has a ton of open uh source
software and a ton of um
uh open research papers.
Somewhat surprisingly, despite smart
speakers having been around for a long
time, it still to this day isn't like a
single architecture that everyone's
agreed on on the best way to do this. If
you look at the literature, there's
still actually diversity of opinions on
how to do this type of wake word or
trigger word. Uh we should also say
this uh
So, when you say something like, you
know, "Okay, Google" or "Hey, Siri" or
"Alexa", that's sometimes called a wake
word cuz it wakes up the device or
trigger word or triggers the device to
take activity. So, somewhat
surprisingly, even though we're smart
speakers for a long time now, for a lot
more than a decade, um
uh there still isn't a single agreed on
unified architecture that the
community's agreed on on what's the best
algorithm to do this. But I feel like
if you are embarking on this for the
first time, um
the number one boost in your speed of
learning, it could be implementing
something, but I would say doing a
literature search and trying open source
software would be the even faster
accelerator.
And I want to give you a few tips for
that, right? Um
real quick.
So, you know, today if if this is um
uh there are a lot of research articles
and blog posts and open GitHub repos on
uh many topics, certainly wake word
detection. And what I find is that um
if this is research paper one, research
paper two, research paper three,
research paper four,
I find that, you know, sometimes people
will um spend a lot of time reading
research paper one until you're done,
right? This is 0% complete. This is 100%
complete.
And they still a lot of time reading
research paper two,
spend a lot of time reading research
paper three,
um and I've just recommend you not do
that. Instead, when
I'm doing a literature search, what it
often feels like is, you know, do a few
web searches for a handful of resources,
skim all of them, 0% complete, 100%
complete, right? Basically, initial
reading, you may decide to go back to
paper C and spend more time to really
read and understand that, but that'll
help you find additional references. You
can skim and maybe you find a paper
seven that's really seminal. Spend a lot
of effort but this is what
doing a very broad survey of the
literature would feel like, where, you
know, you you you really put in the time
to finish only a very small number of
resources, but spend a lot more time
skipping around and giving a cursory
level understanding of a broader set of
papers, which can also point you to um
also point you to the more useful
resources to focus attention on.
>> [snorts]
>> And just one other thing I've seen among
Stanford students, um
uh
there's one other thing that I find
people tend to underuse, which is um
trying to talk to experts. So, if you
are actually a CTO of a startup trying
to build this for the first time,
um I feel like, you know, we all want to
do our own work and not bother other
people, which is good, but I just
encourage you to consider if um
after you've done your own work, if
reaching out to an expert can really
accelerate your learning. So, something
I've often done is, you know, I will do
my own work, right? I don't want to call
random experts to try to bother them
before I have at least done my work. But
if you've uh go Sometimes I'm reading a
paper, I'm really struggling to
understand it, and I find that instead
of me struggling for another like 4
hours, um if I send the authors a
respectful email
uh and say, "Hey, I read your paper,
tried to understand this, I'm still
confused. Can you help me out? Can you
explain this to me?" A lot of the time,
um
uh including when, you know, I I I was
less well known, right? But I think a
lot of people, if they see that you're
doing your work and not just reaching
out to them before you've even done
anything, a lot of them, not everyone,
but a lot of um
research authors would actually be
quite, you know, understanding and and
and try to help you out. And so, I find
that for a lot of projects I did,
um
finding that one expert,
sometimes a sometimes a Stanford
professor, actually we have a lot of
speech faculty in the Stanford faculty
as well, but um when I had problems with
my speech recognition system, you know,
sometimes I call like, you know, Dan
Jurafsky or whatever, and then like a
half hour conversation or even a
10-minute conversation really
accelerates um
what I've been able to do. So, I just
encourage you to um it takes you like 10
minutes to send an email, and maybe
there's a 50% chance of a response, I
don't know, right? Not 100% chance, but
sometimes that tends to be really high
ROI. Right? And then, what I think you
find is that um
if you do a literature search, you will
likely discover that
uh most of the robust enterprise grade
smart speaker systems all have a
specialized system trained to detect the
wake word or the trigger word, right?
And again, there's a variety of
architectures. You probably can't come
up with some good neural network
architectures for this. Um and and and
oh, it turns out that there is no data
set on the internet with lots of people
saying "Robert, turn on", right? That's
just not a thing, right? So, if you
decide that the names are Robert and
Lena and, you know, I don't know, Jeremy
and Alicia or whatever. Sorry, if there
are people with those real names. It was
actually kind of weird when you chose
people's names, but maybe we should
never for some reason. But it turns out
that there is no large data set on the
internet of lots of people saying
"Robert, turn on".
So, if you want to train a neural
network to detect if someone has said
this phrase, you need to collect that
data yourself. Right? Um
So, let me then ask you another
question.
Let's say you've done a literature
search, found some open source code you
can try, but that has led you, say, to
conclude that you need data sets of
people saying "Robert, turn on". Um
uh
you you need a data set to train to
distinguish between someone saying
"Robert, turn on" versus not someone
saying "Robert, turn on". Where would
you How How would you approach getting a
data set like that?
So, yeah, go for it.
Text to speech.
Yeah, cool. Yeah, yep. You use text to
speech as one method. Um this I'll come
back to that later. So, you need that
data, but
Oh, sorry.
Yeah. Yeah, cool. Yeah, I like that.
Yeah, so walk around and ask people.
Tell them what you're doing, get their
permission to record and use their
voice, and then see if they're okay
giving permission, just record their
voices. Yeah, I like that.
Anything else?
Cool. Um yeah.
>> Oh, sorry. Can you say that again? Uh
Oh, yep, cool.
Yeah, yep, cool. Yep, right. So, samples
of people saying not robot turn on is
not people Yeah, you
If you Yeah, cool.
I see, cool. I see.
That's right. So,
people are saying what people are saying
robot, but you don't want that to be a
statement. That's a good point. I'll
come back to that later.
Yes. Did you say something?
Oh, same thing. Oh, interesting. Cool.
Awesome. Great.
All right. So, um
one of the uh
Yes. Uh
so, I really like the idea of you just
going around and asking people for
permission to record their voices. And
then, by the way, in today's world,
privacy is important. Consent is
important. So, you know, don't do
anything sneaky or weird, right? Just
tell people clearly what you're doing.
Ask them for permission. Make sure any
permission is freely given. And if they
don't give permission, it's fine. You
want to really respect people's privacy.
That that is really important. Having
said that, I find that a lot of people
in the world are very nice. Not
everyone, but the vast majority of
people in the world seem very nice. And
if you ask them nicely, you know, I I I
know this cuz I've done this myself.
They will give permission for you to
record, you know, provide their data,
right? Uh
Um
So, and and then just one of the thing
that I encourage you to think about as
always is is a speed. So, how long would
it take you to wander around campus or
wander around San Francisco um and
collect the sample voices? And I think
you actually get a lot done. You'll get
many dozens of samples, maybe hundreds
of samples, easily in a in a day. So, I
think those are good tactics. Um
And then let me share with you some
things. And then um it turns out
synthetic data using text-to-speech is a
interesting tactic. Um
I would usually not use that as the
first thing I do
mainly because it turns out um
I just It's hard to know um how accurate
synthetic data is compared to
true, you know, natural data. And maybe
just share you one thing I've run into.
I've actually, you know, done a lot of
synthetic data for speech recognition,
right? One thing you have to watch out
for is
if you go to a lot of the synthetic, you
know, sources of data, um
how many voices, how many different
voices does it provide? And is it going
to be a pain to get enough, you know,
diversity in different people's voices?
So, it turns out um I don't know. Like,
for example, I
I often, you know, talk to um Open app
voice on my phone, right? Instead of
typing, but the number of voices there
is limited. And if you go to a TTS
provider, I guess there are now some
services with a larger number of voices,
but these are things you end up worrying
about. Uh And it's all solvable. It
Synthetic data does work for speech
recognition, right? But there it turns
out that they're often
enough details associated with filling
with a synthetic data generation process
that ends up taking longer. So, for a
lot of um machine learning applications,
you know, using synthetic data is a good
idea. And eventually you might get
around to it, but using synthetic data
is usually not the first type of data I
would collect
uh because usually there are just too
many hyper parameters and too many knobs
you have to worry about. And then at the
back of your head you'll be wondering
whether there's something you're
weird about the synthetic data that I
have not thought of before. And then
then then once you collect natural data,
collect real data, it's just one fewer
one one less thing to worry about. Um
Maybe just just tell one more story. Um
not in speech, but uh self-driving cars,
right? So, if you're building
self-driving cars, you want to detect
other cars.
Um where do you get pictures of cars?
Uh it turns out that a lot of people
will have the idea of Oh, there's lots
of video games with cars driving around.
Why we use video games to get pictures
of cars out of the video game?
Um
But it turns out a problem with a lot of
video games is there could be like 20
different cars in the entire video game.
Depends on the video game. But it turns
out that to have a realistic video game,
you know, you don't need a thousand
different cars and there are tons of
different car designs on the road, but
you need a very narrow set of cars. And
so, to a human, you know, seeing the
same 20 cars over and over on the road
looks fine. The video game plays fine.
But for a lot of video games, you know,
the data just isn't rich enough to
capture anywhere near the richness of
the real world. Whereas in contrast, if
you got real pictures, there's just one
less thing you have to worry about,
right? So, I find that for synthetic
data,
it works. It's very valuable to use it a
lot, but I usually get to it only later
in the process. Make sense?
Cool. [snorts] Same thing.
So, um
and then
in the interest of building these things
quickly,
let me share with you the types of
things that you know, my teams have done
to collect data for this, right? And And
I I I I feel like, you know, when when
you read research papers or you take,
you know, courses, often you get a very
clean view of data. I'm going to tell
you, you know, uh about one of the weird
random hacks that one of my teams has
used to build like a very serious,
working really well commercial system,
right? And that is at least that's part
of the journey to do so.
Which is um
Let's see. So,
um
Right.
>> [laughter]
>> So, collected
100 training audio clips
and 25 development set to tune to,
and a zero test.
Right. One thing I'll often do if my
main goal is to just build a system that
works as opposed to a published paper is
to not have a test set. We just have a
dev set that we will tune the parameters
to. And if I want to publish a research
paper, I probably need a clean unbiased
test set. But if my goal is to just
build something, you know, and have it
work and ship it, sometimes I just say
I'm not going to bother to collect any
test data. Just a training set and a dev
set and I just unapologetically
tune my system to the dev set. Right.
And one
thing you could do is
um
Let's see.
>> [snorts]
>> So, audio clips
So, audio is um
Let's see. So, you you may have seen the
audio waveforms, right? Which run
through this time. You know, X axis is
time. And audio waveforms kind of are
these wiggly
time series.
Right? And and sound is
very rapid vibrations in the air that
your ear perceives a sound. And what a
microphone does is it records these very
rapid changes in air pressure, right?
So, that's why you see all the waveforms
that look like this.
And um
So, one thing that one of my teams once
did was collected 100 samples of, you
know, audio waveforms where somewhere in
the middle of it um is someone saying
robot turn on.
So, you know, hey, how are you doing?
Oh, yep. And let's let's say robot turn
on. And we can now talk about some other
things,
And so, uh the phrase robot turn on
takes about 1 second to to to say.
And one way to collect a construct a
training set would be
to
take a 3-second clip. So, this is where
robot turn on was said. This is where
they just finished saying robot turn on.
And so, if you collect a
100 audio clips like this,
one way to turn this into bigger
training set is um
to take these small audio clips
and then
this
becomes the training example with a
label one because that's an utterance
where the end of the utterance is
corresponds to when someone just
finished saying robot turn on.
And in contrast,
this would be an example, you know,
would be a negative example.
Um
And this too is a negative example, you
know, and this too
is a negative example.
Does that make sense? So, given a say
10-second clip,
given a 10 seconds of audio,
we will have
cut out um a phrase where
you get a positive label if that
3-second audio corresponds to
someone just finishing saying robot turn
on, which is when you should turn on the
lamp.
Uh and anything else is label zero.
Right? And so, this is a way to take say
100 training examples and turn that into
3,000 binary examples. So, 100 100 audio
clips, sorry. I should say 100 audio
clips.
Right?
And if we take 30 windows out of this,
then you can turn this into
um
say 3,000
training examples, each with a binary 0
1 label.
The labels is this moment in time when
someone just finished saying the phrase
"Robert turn on." Right?
Um
>> [snorts]
>> So, it turns out that if you do this,
and we did do this,
then we wound up
um
Let's see.
We wound up with a system So, we ran
this and uh tested this on the
dev set.
Um
And we wound up with a system that when
trained to predict binary classification
was 97% accurate.
Right?
Uh
But it turns out it did this by
outputting zero all the time. That That
had zero detections.
Right? And so, um
with this training set, we basically
trained a very large neural network
where
I would have gotten exactly the same
result with that one line of Python
code.
>> [snorts]
>> Right?
So, this is a kind of stuff that happens
in real life, right? And And by the way,
I'm showing you these stories not, you
know, just to entertain you. Though,
hopefully you're entertained. But
because I think it is by living these
experiences that you, you know, go, "Oh,
I could see this problem. This is why I
do I could see this problem."
So, my question to you is, if you
collected this data,
trained the system,
97% accuracy, isn't that fantastic?
But you realize that you just
implemented very huge neural network a
print zero statement or the equivalent
of print zero that is never finding the
phrase "Robert turn on."
Right? What what What do you do next?
What's going on with you doing next?
Yeah, cool. Awesome. Right. So, so um
increase the number of "Robert turn ons"
in the training example. This is a very
unbalanced training example. And it's
doing great by just saying, "I never
hear this phrase." Right? How would you
go about And you or anyone else, how
would you go about increasing the number
of positive examples?
Uh go for it.
Oh, but how how how do you do that?
Oh, like wait
Oh, audio assistants. I see. What? I
see. Cool.
Yeah, interesting. Okay, yes. That will
work. It It I guess it's a synthetic
data again, right? Which which is
actually which actually works. And it
also has all the complexities and you
know, but I It turns out it does work.
So, I know it works. So, they're
contacting you, but
Yeah.
But I see. Oh, great.
Yeah. Yep, that works, too. So, um
one thing you could do is uh take your
positive examples, the examples of
"Robert turn on," and just duplicate
those examples. Or or maybe just give
those examples more weight to the
training objective. Right? Yeah. Any
other ideas? Any suggestions?
Oh, increase the noise of the example.
Yeah. Yeah, cool. Yeah, that that that
Yeah. So, a few variations of synthetic
data generation. Yeah. Yep.
So, I think the the the easy things to
try, one would be um
to take the examples and duplicate it,
right? So, you know, mathematically this
is equivalent to taking your positive
examples and just making multiple copies
of that in your training set. Uh it
turns out that will work. That largely
solves it. And by the way, um unbalanced
data sets is a common issue in training
neural networks. I'll tell you the rule
of thumb I use, and you know, is um many
neural networks are pretty good at
handling
up to like a 1 to 10 ratio of unbalanced
data sets. So, people often worry, "What
if an unbalanced data set?" In this
example, we have like a 1 to 30 ratio.
And your mileage may vary. Sometimes it
works, sometimes it won't. In this is In
this In this case, it didn't work. But
um I find that if you have a, you know,
like a 1 to 2 ratio, just usually not
that worried about it. Neural network is
fine training like that. Maybe up to 1
to 10 is when I start to worry about it
being a little bit too unbalanced for
you know, standard training procedures.
And when I might do something to make it
a little bit more balanced.
Um
But duplicating the examples would be
one tactic. Okay. Right.
Uh yes. So, uh penalize uh false
negatives. Yes, that will work, too. So,
I think um
there are a few ways to train the to
change the cost function. You can give
the positive examples more weight or um
uh yes. Or penalize false negatives is
another way to to to uh
change the cost function. That will
work. Yeah. I see.
Right.
Um
it Yeah, go ahead.
Yeah. Yes, so you can also decrease the
number of negative examples. That will
work, too. The one downside of that is
um like it's okay. I think it's fine to
do what she said. The one slight
downside is if you are reducing the
diversity of the negative examples, then
the neural network has just a little bit
less information to learn from. Um I
think this is small What I just said is
a small difference, though. I think that
will also work. It's a quick It's a
quick thing to try.
Yeah.
Um And I I'll just tell you another I'll
tell you what my team actually did. Um
telling you this not because it's a
brilliant technique I'm proud of, but
because I just want to tell you the
examples of the types of hacks that
actual commercial machine learning teams
do that actually works. Right? So, I'll
tell you what we did. It was very close
to duplicating the positive examples,
but we had just a slightly different
variation, which was um
We said that instead of the positive
example being the one window where
"Robert turn on" just finished, so here
where we're having a sequence of labels,
right? Where zero corresponds to
um
is that moment in time when someone just
finished "Robert turn on." And in the
architecture I described, we are
detecting a very very narrow window in
time where someone just finished "Robert
turn on" and you got to turn on.
But the hack that we used was actually
just extend this out a little bit. So,
so instead of saying, "Did someone just
finish saying 'Robert turn on' in the
last, you know,
100 milliseconds?" We extended that out
to half a second or a second. And so, if
someone finished saying "Robert turn on"
anytime in the last half second, let's
turn on the light. Right? And so, this
actually generates a few more training
examples. The reason we did that, again
this is a small difference, is this
actually creates a little bit more
diversity in the positive examples than
just duplicating it. Because now this
red rectangle is a positive example, and
so is this one, and so is this one, and
so is this one. So, it just creates a
little bit more diversity in the
positive examples. Um
I expect this will make a very small
difference in the training
in the learning algorithm's performance,
but it's just, you know, maybe just
slightly better to have slightly
um
Yeah, so it covers the the space of
positive examples just a little bit just
very very
little bit
better.
Um
So, okay, just [clears throat] to keep
going with the story,
um
let's say you do this.
And now
um
you still do well
on the training set.
95% accuracy on the training set,
but um
30% accuracy, so not good enough
on your dev set.
Right? So, you fix one problem,
and another one comes up. And so, what
do you do next?
Go for it.
Yeah, cool. Awesome. Yeah, overfitting
and regularization.
Go ahead.
Um Is it So, right. Is it that training
and dev set distributions are not the
same? In this example,
uh because we collected the training and
the dev sets, if we randomly shuffle
between training and dev, then they
would be the same distribution.
Yeah. But so sometimes um
There's one other thing I do see, which
is uh
if you
It turns out earlier in the history of
machine learning, there was always this
assumption or obsession with making the
training set and the dev set and the
test set have the same distribution. I
think it's because if the training set
and the test set have the same
distribution, it's easier to prove
theorems, easier to give guarantees,
whatever. So, in kind of academic
machine learning, there was always this,
you know, theoretical assumption, which
makes the theory work uh way better, the
training set and the test set come from
the same distribution. Right? It's just
like
from a from a publishing papers point of
view, that makes life much better.
From a practical point of view, what I
see is a lot of the time your training
set distribution is just different than
your test set distribution. Um
That's just life. Because, you know,
it's hard to demand data of a certain
sort. And so, for example, one common
thing is if you do use synthetic data
generation, uh you can come up with
really clever ways to generate synthetic
training data by using TTS, um editing
audio, whatever.
There, these techniques let you generate
a massive training set.
But the price of that is, you know, your
synthetic data, I mean, that's not how
users talk, right? Users don't speak
synthetic data, they speak real data.
And so, to make sure that your test
metric truly reflects how users will
perceive your product,
you know, I would put true data in your
test set. And so, you end up with a lot
of systems where you train synthetic
distribution with synthetic data or
other things you fill it with,
and then your test set is whatever the
world actually cares more about, and the
two distributions is very different.
Um and then I think the question you
just asked is, is the training set
distribution too different from your
synthetic data? Then it's a problem.
Those would be good questions to ask.
Right?
All right.
So, um
if you see this, this is overfitting cuz
we're doing great on training set, not
so well on dev. So, one thing to try
would be the first thing to try is very
regularization. Um so, that would be a
good thing to try.
And then, beyond using regularization, I
find that um for a lot of speech
problems, uh if you're overfitting,
getting more data is nice. And so, just
to share with you, I know I know you
know, the suggestion of synthetic data
earlier, I'll I'll I'll share with you
one thing for synthetic data that does
work, uh which we eventually wound up
using, which is um
it turns out that um
Sorry, this is audio stream, right? It
turns out that there are a lot of uh
uh
if you can get audio clips of background
noise. So, for example, in this room,
you know, if I'm not if I'm quiet, you
can hear a little bit of air
conditioning noise, right? So, a lot of
rooms have little background noise. Or
if you're near a highway, there's car in
the background. So, there are actually
most most people where they may use the
lab, you know, there's a little bit of
background noise.
So, if you're able to get audio of
background noise,
and then additionally, record some very
clean audio clips of Robert turn on,
uh it turns out that if you take two
audio waveforms and sum them together,
you end up with an audio waveform that
sounds like someone saying this in the
presence of the background noise. Right?
So, it's the I think it's called the
superposition property of sound, but
basically sound adds, which is why if
you take two audio clips and you just
add the audio waveforms together, they
end up with an audio recording that
sounds like both sounds going on at the
same time.
So, what you can do is
take, you know,
background noise,
um
there's actually a lot of uh uh
uh audio clips of background noise on
YouTube as well on and so on that check
the licensing terms for you stuff like
that. Right? But there are actually
quite a lot of openly licensed audio
clips of, you know, just someone like a
quiet like a coffee shop noise or or
someone sitting in the hall studying or
whatever. Um
and so, if you can take some background
noise audio clips,
and then take a
clean voice, uh someone saying Robert
turn on,
right? And if you add these two
together,
they end up with background noise,
Robert turn on,
and more background noise, and this
becomes a
positive example using the process that
we
talked about just now.
And if you have a handful of clips of
Robert turn on, and a lot of clips of
background noise, so you can synthesize
the phrase Robert turn on against a lot
of different types of background noise,
and create, you know, a pretty large
training set.
Um it turns out one problem with what I
just described is if you do exactly what
I just said, you won't actually find a
Robert turn on detector, you end up with
a voice activity detection detector,
because you have a lot of background
noise, and anytime anyone says anything,
the only thing people say is Robert turn
on. It's much easier to just decide, is
there a loud sound someone talking? To
actually recognize things. So, the other
thing we should do is um instead of
adding Robert turn on,
you know, pick a dictionary or find
other types of audio that's I I think
that's where you had the comment just
now of make sure you don't confuse other
things, and add, I don't know, get
someone to say the word
you know, I don't know, cardinal or
whatever other words, so you have a
bunch of examples of people saying words
other than Robert turn on, and then also
a bunch of examples of people saying
Robert turn on. And um
by having a handful of clean recordings
of Robert turn on,
uh and a handful of clean recordings of
people saying other stuff, and
synthesizing a data set like this, you
can get a data set with many thousands
of examples
um of Robert turn on pretty efficiently.
Uh and if you train a neural network on
this, you you get like a decent uh wake
word or trigger word detector.
Make sense?
So,
um
>> [snorts]
>> Yeah, right.
So,
with a process like this, um
So, this is what working on a machine
learning project feels like, right? You
try something, doesn't work.
Like you find out that um
you have a skewed data set,
be creative in how you create you
collect data. You may find that you have
a skewed data set, it just doesn't work.
You may find there's overfitting, and
and I find that it is these um the
ability to drive iterations on a system
that determines how quickly
you can get
something to work. Right? Yeah.
Uh um
So, for the Robert turn on example,
>> [laughter]
>> so if I found that there were a lot of
users are listening to music, then um
I would probably synthesize data with
music in the background, and then have
someone say Robert turn on. So, if if
you think a lot of users listen to
music, and there's our dev slam, we want
to make sure we catch them saying Robert
turn on.
Um
uh then I would probably
synthesize more training data to
include, you know, loudish music in the
background.
>> [clears throat]
>> Sorry, what are the genre of music?
>> Oh.
Yeah, so um
it turns out that if you have a I I feel
like uh as a rule of thumb, if you can
have a more diverse set of training
data, it's usually better, right? So,
you know, um
so maybe I'm not sure what music my user
base likes to listen to most. Is it
classical? Is it rock? Is it EDM? Is it
whatever? Um if you could
collect a very rich training set that
includes all of the above and even more,
then um usually that'll do better than
going too narrow and risking picking
wrong. Um
Yeah. And and and the one asterisk to
what I said is uh so long as you can
train a neural network that's big
enough, usually more diverse data, more
data, more diverse data is better.
Uh if your neural network is too small,
then it may lack the capacity or indeed
intelligence to memorize all this stuff,
uh which could be a problem if you need
a very small network that runs at the
edge. But usually, um
usually uh if you have the capacity to
get more rich, more diverse training
data,
that
ends up
delivering better results.
Make sense?
Cool.
Um
All right.
Now,
I want to share with you
So, it turns out um
when you build a machine learning
system,
a very common experience is you try
something and it doesn't work.
And then you have to figure out
all the wonderful ways it could be not
working, and then go and fix whatever is
not working, right? And even in this,
you know, example we went through,
is the training data too skewed? Is it
overfitting? So, you need either
regularization or more data, or is it
like something else? Or does the
synthetic data distribution not match
your data distribution?
It turns out that when you're training a
neural network, when you're
building an AI system,
um
it's really difficult to know in advance
what's going to go wrong next. Uh
I find that in software development, if
I'm writing traditional software,
you know, you kind of control all the
code, and so, it's more okay to write a
spec, and then you just build it, and
then it, you know, kind of works. You
still have to debug it, but the bugs
are, you know, they're my own bugs,
right? In contrast, when you're building
a machine learning system,
it's much more like I don't know what's
going to happen next, right? Maybe
because I don't know what the data will
give me, how to predict how the how the
algorithm will perform. And so, the
workflow of machine learning feels much
more like debugging than development. Um
and by debugging, I mean, it's this
there's a process where you build a
system, and you just repeatedly try to
find how it doesn't work and fix it. Uh
and and and if you're trying to do a
task that humans can do, then the bugs
or the gaps in performance is often
whatever human can clearly do, but the
AI system is unable to do.
So,
for many machine learning teams that,
you know, I've led or worked in,
um, if you can get the team to healthy
rhythm of this debugging cycle, you can
make really rapid progress. So, for
example, it turns out let me give one
example. Um,
I've been on teams where we would do the
following, right? We would say morning,
afternoon,
evening,
night. So, we would run our training
jobs at night, right?
And for example, it turns out for some
of these models we're training for
speech recognition, uh, it takes let's
say it takes 4 hours, right? So, the
training job takes about 4 hours to
train the neural network.
So, train at night, in the morning, um,
we look at the results.
You look at the results, do error
analysis, try to figure out what's
wrong.
Um,
and the afternoon,
you know, we write code, right? To
figure out how we're going to fix
whatever thing we discovered the day
before. And in the evening,
you right before we go home, we launch
the training job.
And then it runs overnight, and the next
morning we do it again and again and
again.
And it turns out that if you can fix one
problem a day,
that's actually pretty good. And within,
you know, like how And then you you you
saw me walk through three three or four
problems. When when I built this
tutorial, there were slightly more
problems than that, right? But I find if
you can get a team into a cadence where
you train stuff, look at the results,
figure out is this bias variance data
mismatch, oh, actually this should be
called on 50 data,
fix it, you know, and in the evening,
before you go home, launch the job.
Maybe if you have time in the evening,
just baby the training job over and make
sure it's still running, but then come
back in the next morning to see how it
did. Then you just do this over and
over, and you can make really rapid
progress. Um,
and I find it's often this discipline,
right? That that lets you make progress.
In contrast, the teams that kind of wake
up and they go, "Huh, what do we do
next? Oh, let's call a meeting this
afternoon. Wait, where's the data? Okay,
I guess we'll meet tomorrow to look at
the data." And then and then like, "Oh,
our infra is down." And teams like that
move much slower than the really
disciplined teams that just keep on
rolling forward.
And
one more observation, it turns out the
iteration cycle, um, sometimes it is
driven by this.
So, I work on machine learning jobs
where it took us about 4 hours to train
a model, and 4 hours is long enough that
I don't want to wait for it, but, you
know, running overnight is just fine.
Um, I've also worked on teams where a
typical training job took about 3 weeks
on average, right? And so, if it takes 3
weeks to train a neural network for a
particular type of model we're working
on, then the pacing is very different.
So, the how long it takes to train a
neural network really drives the pacing
of this, where sometimes we would, you
know, launch a training job and then
like hope for the best. We we monitor
during those 3 weeks. It's not that we
do nothing for those 3 weeks, but you
just going to launch a training job, and
then frankly, you know, hope that it
works 3 weeks later, but we take 3 weeks
and then after that, tons of analysis
and debugging and whatever work that
would take us 1 to 2 weeks to set us up
for the next training job that would
take us another 3 weeks to get the
result. And then we're also
parallelizing. While launching this job,
we're analyzing the result from the
previous job, and we launch a few jobs
asynchronously, but I find that how long
it takes, this is a huge driver for how
you do this.
The other end of the spectrum is if it
takes 10 minutes to train a neural
network, then that's wonderful. You just
train it, get a result, train it, get a
coffee, come back, you know, then do the
analysis, and then the bottleneck is how
quickly you can analyze the data and and
get more data. So, this really drives
the design of this process. Um, and one
of the thing that happens is, uh,
for a lot of projects, you start off
with a small thing that takes 10 minutes
to train, but then as you get more and
more data, you know, then like you
bigger and then now it takes 4 hours to
train. It gets even bigger, then it
takes 3 weeks to train. It's like, "Oh,
now this thing takes a month and a half
to train." So, I've experienced that as
well, where unfortunately, as the
performance climbed, we decided we had
to train bigger and bigger models with
more and more data, and then it went
from this really fantastic 10-minute
iterations to these like months-long
iterations. And but they just had to be
done because we were training bigger and
bigger networks, [clears throat]
right? Yeah.
Um,
we probably didn't stop the model with
that much. Uh,
so sometimes you can look at
checkpoints, um, and if you see that for
some reason, um,
so it it actually if you're training
like a 3-week job, you kind of expect
the performance to be at a certain level
after a couple days or after a week, and
if it's way off, then before burning
another 2 weeks, you would ask, "Is my
learning rate clearly wrong?" Or did Or
maybe this new data set we tried is
clearly wrong. So, you can actually
start to run some analysis in the
checkpoints.
Sometimes we would yank the job and just
cut it. I honestly that happened very
rarely. Uh-uh.
Yeah.
Yeah, yes. So, what what you learn about
in the online videos is I transfer
learning. We train a large data set and
then,
uh, maybe fine-tune on just a much
smaller data set. And then if you
process the fine-tuning on a much
smaller data set, takes, you know, half
an hour, right? Then that's good. Then
you can also drive much faster
iterations than that based on that half
hour so we can factor in the training
time.
>> [snorts]
>> Cool.
All right.
Um,
one reason I obsess about speed is
because, um,
it it it it turns out that's, uh,
if the x-axis Imagine you're building a
startup to launch this product, right?
Um,
I find that it's, um,
if a team takes, you know,
twice as long
to do it, they're just much less
competitive in the marketplace, right?
So, here's what I mean. So, if this is
error
and this is, you know, months, right?
There's some machine learning systems
that we work on for months to to keep on
trying to improve it. And if, um,
this is you,
and if a competitor,
say it takes twice as long to reach the
same level of performance. So, instead
of taking this long to get here, they
take this long to get here. Instead of
taking this long to get here, they take
twice as long to get here. And so, the
competitor kind of does that, right?
Let's just say twice as long. You know,
they take 2 days instead of 1 day to do
something, but they always take 2 days
to do what you would take 1 day to do,
then the performance over time looks
like this.
And what [clears throat] the customer
cares about at a certain moment in time
is you are so much better than them,
right? So, these two x differences in
speed
really translates into a massive
difference in the performance of your
system versus someone else's system in
the marketplace, and,
uh, and and I find that the
fast-moving teams are just so much more
effective. And then you might think,
"Yeah, you know, I took 2 days, they
took 1 day, what's the big deal?" Like,
the big deal is not that you're days
slower, the big deal is you are two
times slower, and very not just in the
marketplace, it's just not competitive
if if you are
if you take twice as long for for for
some for some applications.
Okay?
All right.
There's one other example I want to
cover. Let me try to do that quickly.
>> [clears throat]
>> Um,
So, what I've talked about so far is,
um,
speech recognition, uh, your wake word
detection, which is more of an
end-to-end deep learning system where,
um, you know, your input audio
goes to neural network,
and then this outputs, you know, is this
RTO, robot turn on, right? So, so the
entire system you're trying to build is
just a single neural network.
For a lot of applications you build, you
end up building pipelines, or sometimes
call them cascades. I'm going to use the
term pipelines. We saw one example of
this last time where,
um, to detect people coming up to unlock
a door with face recognition, we had
video that fed to,
visual activity detection to see if
anyone is even in front of it,
and then that fed to neural network to
recognize, you know, is this an
authorized person, and then 0 or 1 to
say is this a person that we should
unlock the door for, right? Um,
what I want to do is use a different
example of a pipeline, uh, of a AI deep
researcher.
So, it turns out all all of the
I think all of the leading, uh, well,
almost all of the leading arm providers,
uh,
have deep researchers, uh, where you can
ask a query or go and search internet,
look at a lot of web pages, and come
back and synthesize a very thoughtful
report, right? Um,
and so, you know, but I I actually use
the Open AI deep researcher quite a lot.
I think that I I I know some of the team
that built it and it's really well
built. Although, I think some of us also
did a good job. But so, you know, you
input a query like um
uh
this this example I'm taking from the
agency AI calls online. Um
but um input a query like show me the
latest research on black holes, right?
Some some query like that.
And then
um
One thing you might do is take a query
like whatever, right? Black hole
research.
And then use an LLM, use a large
language model to generate search terms
to feed to web search engine.
Um
So, it generate a few terms like, you
know, black hole research, latest in I
don't know, astronomy and black holes or
whatever. So, generate a handful of
search terms.
This then call out to web search engine,
uh be it Surfer, Google, DuckDuckGo,
Bing, uh I don't know. I used to really
quite a lot. Uh but of them actually
actually more and more web search
engines designed for AI rather than for
humans, which I think is pretty neat. Um
So, this can
uh call
call the web search engine.
And then fetch the top URLs.
Oh, sorry. I mean, uh fetch the top
pages out of the top URLs.
So, a web search engine returns 10
pages, you may not want to fetch all 10
of them. You can read the snippets,
decide which ones are the most relevant.
Uh again, maybe with an LLM, with a
large language model to decide what are
the pages you want to download. So, just
like a human, you know, do a web search,
I won't click every single link. I'll
take a glance and then decide which ones
I want to click.
Um so, identify and fetch the top URLs
and then feed all that into
writing and this gives the final output.
All right. So, this is a By the way, I
say this is a more traditional deep
researcher article. Uh
sorry, deep researcher architecture. The
more modern deep researcher article
architectures let the system decide when
to do more web search, when to uh fetch
more web pages, and they are more, you
know, autonomous, more agentic. But this
is what the early deep researcher
architectures look like. This more of a
linear pipeline. Then there are more
modern architectures where system will
fetch some pages and autonomously
decide, "Do I need to go back and do
more research on some what topics?" And
iterate a few times. But this would be
like a, you know, pretty decent basic
deep researcher. Right?
And it turns out that if you actually
build this,
um
there one of the
in in the speech recognition system, uh
you know, robot turn on lamp, for
example, we talk a lot about how to
improve one component, which is the
neural network.
If you have a pipeline like this, the
other thing you need to do, which is
critically important, is to decide of
all the different components in the
pipeline, which one do you want to focus
your attention on?
Right? So, I find that um one thing that
makes a huge difference in a team's
performance is again being able to drive
a disciplined evaluation and error
analysis process to decide what to work
on. Uh I find that a lot of machine
learning is not, you know, wildly doing
things to see what works. It's actually
a very thoughtful, very disciplined
process where well, the system
maybe it's not doing as well as we wish.
So, we should look at it to decide um it
turns out lots of things could be wrong.
Is it generating search terms that
aren't quite right? Right?
Or
maybe we're using a web search engine
that is returning results that aren't
that good. So, for example, is um uh is
is is my web search engine comprehensive
enough or is it just, you know, maybe I
picked a lower cost web search service
or something that's just not returning
the latest materials. Um it turns out
for the for for for some internet
articles, many web search engines will
do really well. But if you ever want to
fetch news, really fresh news, there's
actually a lot of difference in the
performance. Some web search engines are
much better at having really fresh
content, some just don't update as
frequently. So, do I need to switch web
search engines?
Or am I successfully [clears throat]
identifying the best web pages to fetch?
So, if I have black hole science, you
know, I think nasa.gov is a very very
authoritative web page. But if a web
page web search engine returns, you
know, like um uh I don't know,
bobsbackyardastronomyblog.com,
right? Uh that's less authoritative than
nasa.gov,
am I correctly fetching the most
authoritative scientific articles versus
whatever is hyped up, you know, or maybe
like uh uh
I don't know, am I fetching a lot of
like random TikTok videos, you know,
rather than really scientific
authoritative things. Um
And then lastly, given all this
information, am I writing a thoughtful
article, right? With an LLM for for the
final research output. So, it turns out
that with a pipeline like this, there
are lots of steps that could go wrong,
and your ability to decide what is the
components you should focus your effort
on, that that's a massive driver of um
your productivity and improving a system
like this.
And the good news is um that there's
actually one other thing I've seen. Um
Sometimes I've seen a few experienced
machine learning people. So, actually
one one thing I've seen, um
sometimes a team will build a system
like this,
uh and it is a less experienced team,
you know, they build a system, it's not
quite working, try to decide what to do
next.
One thing I've seen many times is if you
get a few senior machine learning people
around, but as I said, I've seen this
quite a few times. Sometimes a student's
done a project, maybe a system like
this. If you get a few, you know,
experienced professors to look at the
system, you find that
our opinions on what to do next has
remarkably little variance.
Right? Uh so so you find that many, you
know, experienced AI people look at it
and will go, "Well, based on what it
seems, we think this is a problem or
this is wrong, you should try this."
It's not that we always agree with each
other 100%, but the variance is much
less than you might think. And to me
that, you know, I think there's a
methodology behind how to approach these
problems, whereas the variance in what
to try next among less experienced
engineers is much larger, right? So so I
So, to me I think there's actually um
uh if you have a systematic way of doing
error analysis to figure out where it's
actually underperforming, um you know,
experienced people all kind of Doesn't
mean experienced people are always
right, but there's just no variance,
right? But then there there really is a
methodology to figure out what to do
next.
And one of the key ideas is error
analysis.
Um and I talked about this in online
videos as well, but this is uh
so important, we should go through.
Right?
And um
one thing to do is to look at the
outputs of each of these intermediate
steps.
And it is one of these things, I know
I'll say it, you probably even agree
it's a good idea, but the percentage of
people that will actually do it when the
time comes, I've found to be far lower
than 100%, right? But there's just, you
know,
take a handful of queries, be it is it
um latest in black hole science or
should I rent or buy an apartment or uh
you know, what's the uh what are help me
make fun plans for a weekend in Santa
Cruz, whatever. Some some handful of
queries for a deep researcher.
Um
and then look at what search terms it
generates and see if they make sense.
Look at the web pages it fetches, see if
they look good.
Look at the top pages it fetched and see
if the top web page it selected is
similar or is materially different than
what you would pick. Like my example,
what if this decides to fetch
bobsbackyardastronomypage.com
rather than nasa.gov, right? Then you
go, "Okay, maybe I need to change how I
do that."
Uh and then also look at the final
writing to see given the source
articles, is it writing the appropriate
articles?
And what I find is um
for a process like this,
you know, um
it it it turns out error analysis is
often a very
manual process because when the system
isn't performing,
error analysis or gap analysis is often
a manual process of figuring out what a
human would do that is better than what
the AI system would do, and we're trying
to
inject knowledge from the human into the
AI system. So, because the AI doesn't
have this knowledge yet, uh usually you
do need a human time to do this. And I
know, you know, and people are talking
about automating some of this and maybe
there'll be progress there. But so far I
find error analysis, it just takes human
to look at it and have the insights into
where AI system is doing something
different than an expert human would be.
And it's that insight that then points
you in the direction for how to improve
it.
And um so, for and so often I would
build a spreadsheet like this where I
have a query that is, you know, black
hole science.
And then
another one, do I rent versus buy, you
know, in whatever
San Francisco or uh uh you know, weekend
activities in Santa Cruz.
Right? Whatever. Just
have I don't know, maybe up to 100. I
find that I often have patience looking
up to 100 examples. Uh beyond 100, yeah,
sometimes more than 100, but it's
somewhere between 10 and 100.
Have a list of queries and have list of
steps. Um and so the steps would be
All right, search terms.
Um
What's that? Web search.
Uh
Fetch pages.
So this is what it feels like to do
error analysis. It is a labor-intensive
process because this is a process of
identifying where a human outperforms AI
to try to close the gap. All right, you
just do this over and over.
But so what I would do is I'll sit down
often with a spreadsheet in front of me
open like this and I will run your black
hole signs through the whole system and
then just read are the search terms
satisfactory. Um and if I'm not
explaining black hole signs then we need
to get an expert on do do a bit of work
to figure that out.
But if I find that the black hole the
search terms sent to web search engine
are completely satisfactory then I'll
just say okay, this looks good.
Then given those search terms I'll look
at the web search results and say huh,
did the web search engine retrieve
reasonable things? And it looks good
then great.
And then I'll look at did my system
maybe an LM did it make a good choice in
the top web pages to actually go and
fetch? And maybe I found it's retrieving
it chose to retrieve Bob Bob's
background the strong we want but
skipped nasa.gov. Then I'll say okay,
there's a problem there. All right, and
then often they take a note, you know,
Bob instead of
NASA.
All right, just to kind of just take
notes on on what you're seeing. Um
and then I'll say given these sources is
this writing okay? Maybe it's okay.
And then the process is um
to take a handful somewhere between you
know, 10, 20, and 100 of articles where
the performance is subpar and this
called error analysis because I I want
to focus on where it's underperforming.
All right, so there's some articles that
we're doing a great job on um I would
tend to pay less attention to those but
I'll focus on finding anywhere from 10,
20 to 100 queries where it's clearly
underperforming what I think a human
should be doing or what what I hope this
would do and then going through to just
try to get a sense of how often the
hotspots are in different parts of the
pipeline. And so
maybe for web versus by um I might say
boy, there's really a hard to do blogger
that talks about this but somehow web
search misses. I don't know, maybe I'm
using the wrong web search engine.
Um
we can in Santa Cruz yes, it's it's I
don't know, buying to the you know, some
hyped up tourist things rather than
actually finding locally interesting web
pages and so on.
And then by doing this for
you know, 20, 30, 50
uh queries you can then start to get a
sense of
where the hotspots are. All right, so
again all of these are subpar results.
I'm focusing on queries where the
performance is not good enough.
And then um if I find that, you know, I
don't know, 40% of the time it's failing
to fetch the top web pages, only 5% of
the time all right, it's failing to do
that. Actually let me show you this. We
find that um 70% of the time I'm really
not happy with this. 5% of the time web
search is not good enough, you know,
maybe uh 20% of the time search terms
are wrong and maybe uh
20% of the time the writing's not good
enough. Uh so these don't have to add up
to 100%. Sometimes you have problems in
more than one column.
But if this is what it turns out to be
then we'll go well,
clearly
a lot of the my dissatisfaction with the
results is because it's just not
choosing good pages from the web search
to return. So let me go focus on that.
And the thing about a lot of machine
learning systems is you just don't know
if you don't do this error analysis
ahead of time in terms of what component
to focus on.
Um and so I find that teams that know
how to drive this process systematically
and and it it sometimes takes us hours.
I wrote that you know, daily schedule
thing but sometimes it takes us a few
hours to go through this process to
reach conclusions. But then the benefit
of spending like whatever, you know,
three, four hours on this uh is that it
can save you weeks of otherwise heading
the wrong direction. So um teams can
drive this
error analysis process in a very
methodo- methodo- way um you're much
better picking what direction to work in
and that allows the team to go way
faster. And there's way more than a 2x
difference. So I've actually literally
visited teams that have been working
something for six months and go like
gee, you know, I couldn't have told you
six months ago this wasn't going to cut
it, right? And then then then imagine if
this was the problem we're not writing
the right web pages but you know, for
some reason the team kept on
trying out different web search engines.
Maybe there's someone trying to sell a
new web search service to you. So you
know, spend a lot of time with the sales
team, do a lot of integration with the
web search. Actually there's actually
more web search services than most
people know, right? So and I I actually
swap between them whenever I feel like
it. So so imagine you spend all your
time trying to come up with a better web
search service, you know, for six months
and that's uh it's entirely possible
then you could
just it just won't move the needle for
the overall performance which is why the
circle error analysis process is so
important, right? I walked through this
with the example of one pipeline. Uh the
online videos go through other examples
as well but um uh both for building deep
learning pipelines and for kind of AI
agentic pipelines I think this is a very
important concept to master.